<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Born2Compute</title><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://surendirans.github.io/</id><updated>2023-01-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><subtitle>👨‍💻 Personal Tech Journal 💭</subtitle><entry><title>What you must know about Big data storage?</title><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/posts/What-you-must-know-about-Big-data-storage" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-09-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Surendiran Subramanian</name></author><id>tag:surendirans.github.io,2020-09-19:/posts/What-you-must-know-about-Big-data-storage</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learn how Facebook / Instagram stores and retrieve 500+ TB of daily data quickly.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;We might have surely come across the below two problems probably more than once in your life time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storage Full.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slow File Transfer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p style="display:flex; gap:10px;"&gt;
&lt;img alt="windows-slow-file-transfer" src="https://surendirans.github.io/posts/windows-slow-file-transfer.png" style="width:45%;"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="iphone-storage-full" src="https://surendirans.github.io/posts/iphone-storage-full.jpeg" style="width:45%;"/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today's social media world, we always love to constantly post statuses, videos in Facebook, Instagram, etc.  Have you ever wondered &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;how big tech gaints like Facebook, Instagram manage the above kinds of problems?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-scale-of-data-in-social-media"&gt;The Scale of Data in Social Media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reports says that, during the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; quarter of 2020, Facebook reported almost 1.79 billion Daily Active Users(DAUs).  Overall, DAU's accounted for 66 percent of monthly active users.  This rate is growing more and more day by day.  Every day, we upload massive amount of data to Facebook’s data centre.  Every 60 seconds, more than 136,000 photos are uploaded, 510,000 comments are posted, and 293,000 status updates are posted.  This could account &lt;strong&gt;500+ TBs/day&lt;/strong&gt;.  That's a lot of data.  In-order to give a severity of the problem lets do a quick experiment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="limitations-of-traditional-storage"&gt;Limitations of Traditional Storage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets go and search for the highest available hard disk in the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="maximum-available-storage-in-market" src="https://surendirans.github.io/posts/maximum-available-storage-in-market.png" style="width:80%; display: block;margin: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that the size of hard disk does not exceed more than 10 TBs.  But that is too low storage for these Tech Giants.  We may think that these very big companies having lots of investors, so they might be doing custom manufacturing of hard disk more than 100+ Peta Bytes(PB).  If so then lets go to windows machine containing 1 TB storage, pretty i5 processor running at 2.4GHz and do two experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for a file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy file a file of size 1GB from C to D drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can notice that it would take nearly 5-6 min approx.  Now just imagine searching a post stored in 100+ Peta Bytes of data and copying  500+ Tera Bytes of daily data into Facebook's server.  We might be requiring 7+ days approx to upload and view your posts.  This is surely not a good thing to hear.  Then how these companies over come these kind of problems??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition important"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Important&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above experiment's result may slightly vary depending upon the background processes running in your machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id="distributed-storage-explained"&gt;Distributed Storage Explained&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now lets do the above experiment, but dividing the file into 2 halves - 512 MB (1 GB = 1024 MB) each and coping into two systems separately and simultaneously.  We can clearly note the access time has been reduced to half than before.  What if we divide the file into 4 part and store it in 4 different computers?  What if we divide file into 10 parts, use 10 different computer (generally called as Slave Nodes) and keep one computer(generally called as Master Node) to manage these 10 computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes that's the idea.  This type of storage is called as &lt;strong&gt;Distributed Storage Systems&lt;/strong&gt;.  This becomes the basics for handling big data storage problems.  Real world servers like Facebook's would typically have 15000+ slave-nodes and servers like yahoo would have 4000+ slave-nodes in a cluster (slaves-nodes and master-node combined together called single cluster).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://hadoop.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Hadoop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; help these companies manage such massive amounts of data by distributing storage and computation across all those nodes in the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Big data"/><category term="Hadoop"/><category term="Big data"/><category term="Storage"/></entry><entry><title>What you must know about Computer Memory?</title><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/posts/What-you-must-know-about-computer-memory" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-01-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Surendiran Subramanian</name></author><id>tag:surendirans.github.io,2020-07-20:/posts/What-you-must-know-about-computer-memory</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learn about different types computer memory and why do we need two different types of memories.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Every day we use computers to do lots of complex works.  We use these to do our assignments, projects, simulations, surf webpage, etc.. and off-course writing blogs😉.  Have you ever wondered how computers store the our data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer memory primarily classified into two types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primary memory. (eg: RAM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondary memory. (eg: SSD, Pen-drive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First lets talk about secondary memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="secondary-memory"&gt;Secondary Memory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets think of a situation. You are writing your college assignments in your personal Computer at home.  After completing the your assignments you want to show your work to the concerned Professor.  How would you do that? We mostly probably would copy the file from our computer to the pen drive or to a CD ROM and carry it to the college.  Now note that the data in our pen drive doesn't delete unless the drive gets damaged or we manually delete that file.  Drives with these type of storage properties are called Secondary Storage Devices.  Hard disk in our PC, CD ROM, Flash drives(pen drive), Floppy drives(used earlier), Tape recorder, etc. all comes under this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="primary-memory"&gt;Primary Memory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primary memory is also used to store data. But the problem is that the data in the Primary memory is lost when we turn off our PC (or) we need to constantly supply power to the device else our data will be erased.  Example for these kinds are RAM, Cache, etc.  Primary memory is the place where all our data is loaded before we access it.  For example when we open Notepad, the program for notepad which is stored in hard disk(Secondary Memory) is first loaded into the RAM after that only we can edit the files.  Primary memory plays the major role in our current computer architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="why-do-we-need-two-different-types-of-memories"&gt;Why do we need two different types of memories?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might get a question why do we really need to copy the contents in Secondary memory to Primary memory before accessing it?  Though the Secondary memory has added advantage that it keeps our data even when the computer is Turned off. Why can't we access the files directly in secondary memory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To know the answer for these lets do some experiment. First lets have a video file of more than 1GB in our pen-drive.  When we plug it in our system and double click it. We notice that the video plays immediately. Now lets try to do forward our video to some random time stamp.  Again we notice that the video plays immediately.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now lets try to copy that video to our PC. You may notice that it takes some time to do that.  Because the access speed of Secondary Memory is considerably low when compered with the Processor.  On an average a typical Processor(CPU) would have around 2.4 - 3.8 GHz clock frequency, where as secondary storage would have around only 80 - 200 MHz (HDD).  This is main reason to go for Primary memory which has 2.4 - 2.8 GHz.  The difference in the access speed of primary and secondary memory is because the type of electronic circuit, each made up of is completely different.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Computer Memory"/><category term="Memory"/><category term="Storage"/></entry></feed>