<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Born2Compute - Computer Memory</title><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/feeds/computer-memory.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://surendirans.github.io/</id><updated>2023-01-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><subtitle>👨‍💻 Personal Tech Journal 💭</subtitle><entry><title>What you must know about Computer Memory?</title><link href="https://surendirans.github.io/posts/What-you-must-know-about-computer-memory" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-01-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Surendiran Subramanian</name></author><id>tag:surendirans.github.io,2020-07-20:/posts/What-you-must-know-about-computer-memory</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learn about different types computer memory and why do we need two different types of memories.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Every day we use computers to do lots of complex works.  We use these to do our assignments, projects, simulations, surf webpage, etc.. and off-course writing blogs😉.  Have you ever wondered how computers store the our data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer memory primarily classified into two types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primary memory. (eg: RAM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondary memory. (eg: SSD, Pen-drive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First lets talk about secondary memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="secondary-memory"&gt;Secondary Memory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets think of a situation. You are writing your college assignments in your personal Computer at home.  After completing the your assignments you want to show your work to the concerned Professor.  How would you do that? We mostly probably would copy the file from our computer to the pen drive or to a CD ROM and carry it to the college.  Now note that the data in our pen drive doesn't delete unless the drive gets damaged or we manually delete that file.  Drives with these type of storage properties are called Secondary Storage Devices.  Hard disk in our PC, CD ROM, Flash drives(pen drive), Floppy drives(used earlier), Tape recorder, etc. all comes under this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="primary-memory"&gt;Primary Memory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primary memory is also used to store data. But the problem is that the data in the Primary memory is lost when we turn off our PC (or) we need to constantly supply power to the device else our data will be erased.  Example for these kinds are RAM, Cache, etc.  Primary memory is the place where all our data is loaded before we access it.  For example when we open Notepad, the program for notepad which is stored in hard disk(Secondary Memory) is first loaded into the RAM after that only we can edit the files.  Primary memory plays the major role in our current computer architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="why-do-we-need-two-different-types-of-memories"&gt;Why do we need two different types of memories?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might get a question why do we really need to copy the contents in Secondary memory to Primary memory before accessing it?  Though the Secondary memory has added advantage that it keeps our data even when the computer is Turned off. Why can't we access the files directly in secondary memory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To know the answer for these lets do some experiment. First lets have a video file of more than 1GB in our pen-drive.  When we plug it in our system and double click it. We notice that the video plays immediately. Now lets try to do forward our video to some random time stamp.  Again we notice that the video plays immediately.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now lets try to copy that video to our PC. You may notice that it takes some time to do that.  Because the access speed of Secondary Memory is considerably low when compered with the Processor.  On an average a typical Processor(CPU) would have around 2.4 - 3.8 GHz clock frequency, where as secondary storage would have around only 80 - 200 MHz (HDD).  This is main reason to go for Primary memory which has 2.4 - 2.8 GHz.  The difference in the access speed of primary and secondary memory is because the type of electronic circuit, each made up of is completely different.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Computer Memory"/><category term="Memory"/><category term="Storage"/></entry></feed>